<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_allPlus.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="corpus9" type="work">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <!--INFORMATION ON THE ELECTRONIC EDITION-->
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Les archives royales du Maṣḥāfa Ṭefut à la cour de Gondar</title>
          <principal>
            <persName>
              <forename>Manfred</forename>
              <surname>Kropp</surname>
            </persName>
          </principal>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>création du fichier électronique et responsable de l'édition électronique</resp>
            <persName>
              <forename>Cyril</forename>
              <surname>Masset</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName>
              <forename>Anaïs</forename>
              <surname>Wion</surname>
            </persName>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Révision du fichier électronique (avril 2011)</resp>
            <persName>
              <forename>Lou</forename>
              <surname>Burnard</surname>
            </persName>
          </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt xml:id="editionStmt9" xml:lang="fra">
          <p>draft for electronic publishing</p>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>Institut de Recherche et d'Histoire des Textes</publisher>
          <authority>Section de diplomatique</authority>
          <address>
            <postCode>45071 Orléans</postCode>
            <name n="F">France</name>
          </address>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <!--DESCRIPTION OF THE MANUSCRIPT-->
          <p/>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <!--DESCRIPTION OF THE CORPUS : à encoder pour le filtre CORPUS-->
      <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
          <p>The ms. <ref corresp="BLorient481">BL Or 481</ref> is a Bible ms. (Octateuch and Gospels), illuminated by miniatures. these are of great importance for the history of Ethiopian art and book illumination. The codex is an exact copy of the mäṣḥafä ṭefut to be found till today in the church Ǝgziʾbǝḥer-Ab on Amba Gǝše(n), Wollo. The copy probably was made during the reign of emperor Śärṣä-Dǝngǝl, end of 16th century. Besides the main text there is a number of documents written at the end of chapters or on originally blank pages. These documents, written by different hands and at different times, were carefully copied into the ms. <ref corresp="BLorient481">BL Or 481</ref>, but there written by the same hand as the main text, but inserted at the same places as in the mäṣḥafä ṭefut. These documents refer mostly to churches on Amba Gǝše(n), territories nearby and members of the royal Ethiopian family. As for their textual nature they are juridical documents, issued by the emperors of the time or by other secular or ecclesiastical authorities. Furthermore they are treating juridical acts of different kind: from donations of land or their revenues to churches or monasteries, but to individuals as well, over precise lists of taxes and services bound to plots of land to royal decrees of every kind, touching private affairs as well as the re-establishing "good old" regulations of the court. This is true for the first series of documents, dating from the end of the 13th to the end of the 16th century and common to the original codex and its Gondarine copy. In the Gondarine codex (<ref corresp="BLorient481">BL Or 481</ref>) the practice of inserting juridical documents dontinued. There is in fact a series of documents, written by different hands, dating from the beginning of the 17th till the middle of the 19th century, and referring mostly to the church Däbrä-Bǝrhan-Śǝlasse in Gondar. That is why one presumes that the ms. was originally property of and housed in this church.
            The aim of the actual research is the diplomatic edition of all the juridical documents contained in <ref corresp="BLorient481">BL Or 481</ref>, then the translation and commentary of these complicated, non-literary, pragmatical texts.</p>
        </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2017-07-19" who="AW">Création du fichier xml</change>
      </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>     <text><body><ab/></body></text>
  </TEI>