<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="nar" xml:lang="en" xml:id="NAR0213MichaelTemple"><teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt><title type="full"><span xmlns="" class="w3-tag w3-red">No item: NAR0213MichaelTemple</span></title>
                <title>Conversion of the Temple in Alexandria to the Church of St Michael</title>
                <editor role="generalEditor" key="AB" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/team.html#AB" xml:id="AB">Alessandro Bausi</editor>
                <editor key="ES" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/team.html#ES" xml:id="ES">Eugenia Sokolinski</editor>
                <funder>Akademie der Wissenschaften in Hamburg</funder>
            <respStmt xml:id="ed-AB" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/team.html#AB"><resp>general editor</resp><name>Alessandro Bausi</name></respStmt><respStmt xml:id="ed-ES" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/team.html#ES"><resp>editor</resp><name>Eugenia Sokolinski</name></respStmt></titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Hiob-Ludolf-Zentrum für Äthiopistik</authority>
                <publisher>Die Schriftkultur des christlichen Äthiopiens und Eritreas: Eine multimediale
                            Forschungsumgebung / Beta maṣāḥǝft</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/"> This file is
                                licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0. </licence>
                </availability>
            <date type="expanded">9.4.2025 at 15:10:18</date><date type="lastModified">16.12.2024</date><idno type="collection">narratives</idno><idno type="url">https://betamasaheft.eu/narratives/NAR0213MichaelTemple/main</idno><idno type="URI">https://betamasaheft.eu/NAR0213MichaelTemple</idno><idno type="filename">NAR0213MichaelTemple.xml</idno><idno type="ID">NAR0213MichaelTemple</idno></publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>A digital born TEI file</p>
        <p>Encoded according 
                        to the <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/">Beta maṣāḥǝft Guidelines</ref>. 
                        These Guidelines detail the TEI format ruled by 
                        the <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu/Guidelines/?id=schemaView">Beta maṣāḥǝft Schema</ref>. 
                        The present TEI file is enriched with an 
                        <ref target="https://github.com/BetaMasaheft/BetMas/blob/master/db/apps/BetMas/modules/expand.xqm">Xquery transformation</ref> 
                        taking advantage of the <ref target="https://betamasaheft.eu">exist-db database instance</ref> where 
                        the data is stored and of the many external resources to which this data points to.</p><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="bm" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="https://www.zotero.org/groups/358366/ethiostudies/items/tag/bm:$1"/><prefixDef ident="betmas" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="https://betamasaheft.eu/$1"/><prefixDef ident="ethiocal" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/BetaMasaheft/BetMas/master/BetMas/calendars/ethiopian.xml#$1"/><prefixDef ident="pleiades" matchPattern="(\d-3)" replacementPattern="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/$1"/><prefixDef ident="sdc" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="https://w3id.org/sdc/ontology#$1"/><prefixDef ident="wd" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="https://www.wikidata.org/entity/$1"/><prefixDef ident="snap" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://data.snapdrgn.net/ontology/snap#$1"/><prefixDef ident="saws" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://purl.org/saws/ontology#$1"/><prefixDef ident="skos" matchPattern="([a-za-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#$1"/><prefixDef ident="gn" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#$1"/><prefixDef ident="dcterms" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://purl.org/dc/terms/$1"/><prefixDef ident="dc" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://purl.org/dc/terms/$1"/><prefixDef ident="lawd" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://lawd.info/ontology/$1"/><prefixDef ident="syriaca" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z\-]+)" replacementPattern="http://syriaca.org/documentation/relations.html#$1"/><prefixDef ident="agrelon" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://d-nb.info/standards/elementset/agrelon.owl#$1"/><prefixDef ident="rel" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z]+)" replacementPattern="http://purl.org/vocab/relationship/$1"/><prefixDef ident="em" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="https://www.eagle-network.eu/voc/material/lod/$1"/><prefixDef ident="eo" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="https://www.eagle-network.eu/voc/objtyp/lod/$1"/><prefixDef ident="ew" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="https://www.eagle-network.eu/voc/writing/lod/$1"/><prefixDef ident="ic" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="http://iconclass.org/$1"/><prefixDef ident="ecrm" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/$1"/><prefixDef ident="foaf" matchPattern="([a-zA-Z0-9]+)" replacementPattern="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/$1"/></listPrefixDef><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="xmldb:exist:///db/apps/lists/canonicaltaxonomy.xml"><xi:fallback><p>Definitions of prefixes used.</p></xi:fallback></xi:include><source-url><assertion unit="edition" match="//div[@type='edition']" use="@xml:id" log="."/></source-url></encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <abstract>
                <p>Story of the conversion of the temple in Alexandria which was built by <persName ref="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS3137Cleopatr">Cleopatra</persName> into a 
                    church dedicated to St Michael as a commemorative notice for the month of Sane as it is the case in the Sǝnkǝsār (<ref type="work" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT4035SenkessarDL#Sane12Mikael">for 12 Sane</ref>). Taken from 
                    the history of Bāḥrān and very similar to the stories of Talafinos and Talason in <ref type="work" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT3959Homily">Homily on the Archangel Michael by Epiphanius</ref>, 
                    <ref type="work" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT7176MiracleMichaelTalason">Miracle of St Michael about a child (Talason) that
    was thrown into the sea</ref> and <ref type="work" corresp="https://betamasaheft.eu/LIT1295Dersan#HomilyTalason"><span xmlns="" class="w3-tag w3-red">No item: LIT1295Dersan#HomilyTalason</span></ref>
                    
                  </p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term key="ChristianLiterature" ana="#ChristianLiterature"/>
                    <term key="Hagiography" ana="#Hagiography"/>
                    <term key="Miracle" ana="#Miracle"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gez">Gǝʿǝz</language>
            </langUsage>
        <calendarDesc><calendar xml:id="world"><p>ʿĀmata ʿālam/ʿĀmata ʾəm-fəṭrat (Era of the World)</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="ethiopian"><p> ʿĀmata śəggāwe (Era of the Incarnation –
                                    Ethiopian)</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="grace"><p>ʿĀmata məḥrat (Era of Grace)</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="diocletian"><p>ʿĀmata samāʿtāt (Era of Martyrs (Diocletian))</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="alexander"><p> Era of Alexander</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="evangelists"><p>Evangelists' years</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="islamic"><p>Hiǧrī (Islamic)</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="hijri"><p>Hiǧrī (Islamic) in IslHornAfr</p></calendar><calendar xml:id="julian"><p>Julian</p></calendar></calendarDesc></profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#ES" when="2024-12-16"><!--{let $resp := $node/@who return $expand:editorslist//t:item[@xml:id = string($resp)]/text()}: -->Created entity</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader><standOff><listRelation>                    
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about" active="https://betamasaheft.eu/NAR0213MichaelTemple" passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS3137Cleopatr"/>
                    <relation name="ecrm:P129_is_about" ref="http://erlangen-crm.org/current/P129_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/is_http://erlangen-crm.org/current/about" active="https://betamasaheft.eu/NAR0213MichaelTemple" passive="https://betamasaheft.eu/PRS7049Michael"/>
                </listRelation></standOff><text>
        <body>
            <div type="bibliography">
                
            </div>
            <div type="translation"><note>After Synaxarion for 12 Sane</note>
                <ab>There was in the city of
                    Alexandria a great temple which Queen Cleopatra, the daughter of Ptolemy, King of
                    Egypt, had built in the name of the star Zuhal (Venus), and they celebrated a festival in its
                    honor on the twelfth day of the month of Sane. And there was in that temple a great brass idol which was exceedingly awesome, and its name was Zuhal (Venus), and they used to
                    offer up many sacrifices to it on the day of the festival; and they continued to celebrate the
                    festival of that idol until the days of the archiepiscopate of Archbishop Alexander, that is
                    to say for three hundred years and more. When Abba Alexander was appointed
                    Archbishop of Alexandria, the righteous Emperor Constantine was reigning, and the True
                    Christian Faith spread abroad. And Abba Alexander wanted to smash that idol, but some
                    worthless men of the city prevented him, and they said unto him, “We are in the habit of
                    celebrating a festival in honor of this idol. And behold, fifteen archbishops have preceded
                    thee [here], and they did not alter our custom.” And Abba Alexander rebuked them
                    severely, and he explained the matter to them, and said, “This idol can do neither evil nor
                    good, but those who celebrate the festivals of idols worship Satans.” And Abba Alexander
                    also said unto them, “If ye will hearken unto my advice, let me arrange for you this festival
                    as it ought to have been in olden times, that is to say, let us smash this idol, and
                    [re]consecrate the temple, and turn it into a church in the name of the glorious angel
                    Michael, the Archangel, and we will arrange this festival in his honor. And let the altar be
                    [re-dedicated] to God Most High, and let the poor, and the needy, and the wretched, eat the
                    oxen and sheep which the priests slay, and the glorious angel Michael shall intercede on
                    your behalf with our Lord Jesus Christ.” And this good counsel pleased them, and they
                    yielded to his wishes, and they made the temple a church in the name of the glorious angel
                    Michael the Archangel. And that temple became known as the “Church of Caesarea,” and
                    it continued to stand until the Muslims reigned in Egypt, and then they destroyed it. And
                    this festival was established by order, and all the people of the districts [in Egypt]
                    celebrated it in honor of the glorious angel Michael the Archangel to his grade, above all
                    the angels, and to his greatness, and the archangel performed many miracles among which
                    is the following: There was a certain man who feared God, and who used to celebrate the
                    commemoration of the glorious angel Michael on the twelfth day of each month, and
                    especially during the months of Hedar and Sane. And there was among his neighbors a
                    rich man who was without mercy, and he used to hate that God-fearing man when he
                    celebrated the festival of the glorious angel, and to laugh at him. When the days of the
                    God-fearing man had come to an end, and the time of his death, when he would rest from
                    the labor of this fleeting world, drew nigh, he commanded his wife to be merciful, and to
                    celebrate the commemoration of that glorious angel Michael, and especially the festivals
                    which fell on the twelfth day of Hedar and on the twelfth day of Sane. Now at the time of
                    the death of the God-fearing man, his wife was with child. And after the man died his wife
                    buried him. And at that time the woman was near her time to bring forth, and the pains of
                    childbirth seized her, and she was in very great tribulation, and she said, “O Michael, angel
                    of God, have compassion upon me, and entreat God on my behalf so that He may deliver
                    me from the tribulation in which I am, and which hath come upon me this day; for with
                    thee there is great grace with God.” And when she had said these words, the house
                    wherein she was became full of light, and forthwith she was relieved of her pains, and she
                    brought forth a child whose appearance was godly. And the angel of God, the glorious
                    Michael, came down from heaven, and he blessed the child, and said, “Thus saith God:
                    This child shall inherit the goods of the rich man who hath no mercy, and all his
                    possessions and all his lands.” At that moment the rich man was looking out from the
                    window of his house upon the house of the woman, and he heard the voice of Michael, the
                    angel of God, saying, “This child shall inherit the money of the rich man.” Then great
                    sorrow came upon him, and he sought for a pretext for killing the child, but God protected
                    him through the intercession of the glorious angel Michael. And when the days of the child were ten years, his mother’s money came to an end, and the rich man, with small
                    mercy in him, found his opportunity against the woman. And he said unto her, “Give me
                    thy son, and let him minister unto me, and I will feed him and clothe him, and will give
                    thee twenty dinars in gold.” When the woman heard these words from the rich man she
                    rejoiced on account of her poverty, and the rich man gave her twenty dinars in gold, and
                    she gave him her son; and having taken him the rich man rejoiced with a great joy, and he
                    said in his heart, “Behold what I have desired is fulfilled for me.” Then he made a wooden
                    box as long as the boy was tall, and he forced the boy into the box, and fastened the cover
                    over him, and he carried the box to the river, and cast it into the water, and he also cast the
                    key of the box into the river. And by the Will of God the box floated on the surface of the
                    river until it came to the quay of a certain city, which was not far from the river. And there
                    was a certain shepherd who was watching and tending his flocks near the river, and when
                    he saw the box in the river, he dragged it out, and carried it into his house, and he was
                    thinking by what means he would open the box. And as he was thinking about this matter,
                    God put the thought into his heart that he should go to the river, and straightway he went
                    and found a man catching fish. And the shepherd said unto him, “Cast [thy] net into the
                    river in my name, and I will give thee the price of the fish which shall be caught”; and the
                    fisherman did as the shepherd told him. And a great fish came out from the net, and the
                    shepherd gave him the price thereof; and taking it he went to his house, and he killed the
                    fish to broil it, that he and his household might eat. And having slit open the belly of the
                    fish he found a key inside it, and he said within himself, “Perhaps this is the key of the
                    box.” And having inserted the key into the keyhole of the box, the box opened quickly,
                    and the shepherd marveled for he found inside it the boy whom the rich man wanted to
                    kill. When he saw [the boy] he rejoiced in him with a great joy, and he called him
                    “Bahran” because he found him in the river; and the boy became to him as his son. Now
                    the distance of the city wherein the boy was born, from that wherein the shepherd lived,
                    was a journey of ten days. And after many days the rich man in whom there was no mercy
                    wished to go and sojourn with the shepherd, and when the sun was about to set he said
                    unto the shepherd, “Peradventure thou hast a place wherein we can lodge until to-morrow;
                    if thou hast I will pay thee thy charge.” And the shepherd brought the rich man into his
                    house, and he called the young man by his name of “Bahran.” When the rich man heard
                    this name he asked the shepherd, saying, “Is this thy son?” And the shepherd said unto
                    him, “Yea, I found this young man when he was a little boy in a box in the river, and I took
                    him and reared him as my son.” When the rich man, in whom there was no mercy, heard
                    this he was very sorry in his heart, and he knew that the young man was the boy whom he
                    had thrown into the river to kill him. And on the morrow the rich man wished to depart,
                    and he devised a device of Satan and said unto the shepherd, “I want thee to give me this
                    thy son so that I may send him with a message to my house in the city which is called Soand-so, because I have forgotten something which is in my house; and the payment of
                    twenty dinars of gold which I should give to him I will give to thee.” And the shepherd
                    rejoiced because of the gold, and he called the young man and said unto him, “O my son
                    Bahran, come that this honorable man may send thee to his house on some business
                    concerning his house, and return to my house in peace”; and the young man said unto him,
                    “Willingly, O my father, whatsoever thou commandest me I will do.” Then straightway
                    the rich man wrote a letter to his steward, saying, “When thou hast read this letter kill the
                    bearer of it, whose name is ‘Bahran,’ and cast his body into a pit. Let no one know about
                    this until I come in peace”; and he wrote on the letter a certain sign which they had agreed
                    upon, and which none but they two knew. And he sealed the letter and gave it to Bahran, and he gave him what money was needful for the journey, and the young man departed.
                    And as he was journeying along the road, he was about half-way between the two cities,
                    behold one day the angel of God, Michael, the Archangel, came to him, riding upon a
                    horse in the form of a soldier of the emperor; and he said unto Bahran, “What hast thou
                    with thee?” And he said unto him, “I have with me a letter from a rich man who hath sent
                    me to his house in such and such a city.” And the angel of God, the glorious Michael, said
                    unto him, “Show me the letter,” and Bahran being afraid of him gave him the letter. And
                    the angel blew on the paper, and obliterated everything, which was written upon it. And
                    the glorious angel, Michael, the Archangel, wrote with his own hand on the paper, saying,
                    “Behold, I the rich man So-and-so have sent unto thee the bearer of this letter whose name
                    is Bahran. As soon as ye have read this letter marry my daughter So-and-so to him, I have
                    given him all the goods in my house, and all my lands. Do not wait until I come back, for I
                    shall tarry on my journey. Let him do what he wisheth in my house, for I have given him
                    authority over all my goods and over my house. Here is the sign which is between thee
                    and me, O my steward, So-and-so.” And the angel of God, the holy angel Michael, the
                    Archangel, sealed the letter, and gave it to Bahran, and said unto him, “Go to the house of
                    the rich man, and when thou hast arrived at his house give this letter to his steward, and do
                    not tell him that I met thee on the road, and that I have changed [the contents of] this
                    letter.” And Bahran said unto him, “Yea, my lord, everything which thou hast commanded
                    me I will do.” And Bahran went on until he arrived at that city, and he enquired for the
                    house of the rich man So-and-so, and one brought him to it, and he gave his letter to his
                    steward. And when the steward had read it, and understood the contents thereof, he
                    recognized the [private] mark, and knew that it was authentic. And forthwith they made a
                    great marriage-feast for Bahran and the daughter of the rich man, and they married them in
                    the church, before the sanctuary of God; and they lived in the happiness of marriage for
                    forty days. And towards the end of the marriage-feast the rich man returned to his city,
                    and when he heard the sound of the music and singing, and the rejoicings, he asked,
                    saying, “What is this sound which I hear?” And certain of the men said unto him, “Thy
                    letter came by the hand of a young man called Bahran, and as in it thou didst command
                    that thy daughter should be married to him, they gave her to that young man whose name
                    is Bahran. And behold they have been rejoicing in the marriage-feast forty days and forty
                    nights. And they have given him all thy money, and thy house, and menservants and
                    handmaidens, and all thy possessions, according to what thou didst command in thy
                    letter.” And when the rich man heard these words, he cried out at the top of his voice, and
                    fell down and died; and straightway the Satans took his soul into the lowest Hades. And
                    the young man inherited all his money even as God the Most High had commanded. And
                    the young man Bahran celebrated the commemoration of the glorious angel of God,
                    Michael the Archangel, on the twelfth day of each month, and he knew that it was he who
                    had appeared unto him and breathed on the letter and obliterated what was written therein,
                    and had written other matter in its place. And after this he built a beautiful church in the
                    name of the glorious angel Michael, the Archangel, and he painted a picture of him in it in
                    front of the sanctuary, and through this picture many signs and wonders were made
                    manifest, and the sick were healed. And Bahran was appointed priest of that church, and
                    he ministered therein until the day of his death, and his mother and his son inherited
                    everlasting life through the intercession of the glorious and holy angel, Saint Michael, the
                    Archangel. And on the day of the resurrection this glorious angel bowed before the throne
                    of God, and said, “I beg and entreat Thy compassion, O my God, I Thy servant and
                    messenger, to make known to me all those who celebrate my commemoration upon earth, through Thy righteous promise, for Thou art merciful and compassionate.” And God
                    answered and said unto him, “O Michael, chief of the faithful hosts of heaven, behold, I
                    command thee to lift up upon thy wing of fire as many [men] as thou art able to carry upon
                    it, three times.” And when Saint Michael heard this he rejoiced and was glad, and he lifted
                    up upon his wing three times [as many as he could of] the men who celebrated his
                    commemoration upon earth and made them to pass by the river of fire. And there were
                    thousands of thousands and tens of thousands of tens of thousands, and no one could
                    number them except God Himself. Therefore, O beloved, it is meet that we should strive,
                    and should celebrate the commemoration of the glorious angel Michael, the Archangel, as
                    well as we are able, even if it be only to give a cup of cold water in his name, even as our
                    Lord saith in His Holy Gospel. And let us ask for mercy from God through the
                    intercession of the glorious angel Michael, that He may deliver us from the net of Satan,
                    the accursed, and may put far away from us all pain (or, sickness) and the plague, and may
                    increase the fruits of our lands in performing His mercy, and may forgive us our sins, and
                    may give rest to the souls of our dead, and may bring back in safety those of our fathers
                    and brethren who are on a journey, and may set peace in our midst, and may strengthen us
                    in the True Faith to our last breath. And this glorious angel Saint Michael the Archangel
                    performed many miracles. </ab></div>
        </body>
    </text></TEI>